# **Mykolas Viningas**

■ m.viningas@gmail.com • London, UK ★ mykolasviningas.github.io

#### **PROFILE**

I am a full-stack software engineer with multiple years of experience designing, building, and solving in the Ruby, JavaScript, and Go ecosystems. Most recently, I co-created Symphony , an open-source framework that provides real-time collaboration functionality and ready-to-scale infrastructure to web applications.

# **PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE**

#### **Creator, Software Engineer,**

2023 - present

Symphony (symphony-framework.github.io) ☑

An open-source real-time collaboration framework

- Researched and decided on the components to be provisioned, including real-time infrastructure and state convergence
- Implemented preservation of shared application state (document) by checkpointing and storing the documents in binary form to object storage (AWS S3)
- Designed the schema for a PostgreSQL database (AWS RDS) and implemented persistence of server metadata
- Simplified the monitoring and debugging of the system by building a dashboard interface that provides metric data about connections and documents (React, TypeScript, Tailwind)
- Wrote a RESTful API (Node.js/Express) for delivering server metadata to the dashboard client, including live metrics (SSE)
- Created an API and built an NPM package for a client library (JavaScript) that connects to the WebSocket server
- Abstracted away the backend management by containerizing (Docker, AWS ECR) and moving the architecture from AWS EC2 to AWS ECS deployed in Fargate mode
- Separated concerns by decoupling the backend into individual services for Dashboard and WebSocket clients
- Provided a single point of entry to different services and traffic routing to individual instances of the WebSocket server by configuring an application load balancer (AWS ALB)
- Engineered a custom load-testing solution (AWS EC2, Docker) to extract the performance metrics of the WebSocket server and identify the bottlenecks under as close to real-life conditions as possible
- Increased the number of concurrently connected clients handled by the WebSocket service from 240 to 10,000 (40x) by horizontally scaling the WebSocket server using publisher/subscriber model (AWS ElastiCache for Redis) and allowing server-to-server querying for application state (AWS DynamoDB)
- Contributed to building a CLI application that uses the AWS CDK and SDK libraries to automate infrastructure deployment
- Authored Symphony's case study: symphony-framework.github.io
- Collaborated as part of a remote team of 4 engineers across 2 timezones using Agile workflow

### **Software Engineer,** *Self-employed*

2019 - 2022

Some of the projects and technologies used during this time:

- Terminal a real-time application for receiving and debugging webhooks (Next.js/React, TypeScript, ChakraUI, Node.js, Express, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, WebSockets)
- Progress Pal a database-backed productivity application for managing tasks and goals (Ruby, Sinatra, PostgreSQL, JavaScript, jQuery, HTML, CSS)
- Contact Helper a contact manager application that lets you save and sort contacts by different categories with Model-View-Controller structure on the front-end (Node.js, Express, JavaScript, Handlebars, HTML, CSS)

# **SKILLS**

# **Back end**

Node.js, Express, Ruby, Sinatra, Go, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, RESTful APIs

# Tooling

Git/GitHub, Docker, Linux, Bash, Nginx, Pm2

## Front end

JavaScript, TypeScript, jQuery, React/Redux, Next.js, HTML, CSS

#### Cloud

AWS, DigitalOcean Droplets, Heroku

### **EDUCATION**

**Launch School** ☑ 2019 – 2022

A mastery-based study of Software Engineering fundamentals

# Royal Academy of Music, University of London,

2013 - 2017